Finding Aid for William Augustus Lewis Papers, 1840-1917
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
William Augustus Lewis papers 1840-1917
Lewis, William Augustus, 1825-1917.
2 linear feet
87479 Aa 2
Officer with the 23rd Michigan Volunteer Regiment during the Civil War, later Saginaw County, then Evart, Michigan, local government official. Biographical material, correspondence, Civil War files, and diaries relating to local and wartime activities, family matters, and professional activities.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Lewis' grandson, Professor Ralph W. Lewis (donor no. 7394 ) in September 1986.
The collection is open to research.
William Augustus Lewis was born in Harvard, Massachusetts on December 11, 1825. His family moved to Mt. Clemens, Michigan in 1835. Around 1849, his father left for the California Gold Rush and never returned to his family.
In September of 1862 William Lewis went into the 23rd Michigan Volunteer Army Corps. He served as First Lieutenant, Captain, and Acting Assistant Adjunct General. During the Civil War he also worked as a correspondent for his brother's (George F. Fred) Lewis, 1828-1890) newspaper, "The Saginawian."
Upon the regiment being disbanded in June of 1865, William returned to his mother's home in Mt. Clemens, Michigan, only to move to Saginaw where he began the practice of Law.
On December 14, 1865 William married Sarah J. McKnight of Saginaw. Together they had three children; a daughter who died in childhood, Ralph A., and George F. (Fred) Lewis.
Between 1865 and 1876 he served as Circuit Court Commissioner of Saginaw County for four years.
Lewis opened a law firm in Evart, Michigan in 1872. Thereafter he occupied several local government positions. He was instrumental in preparing the paperwork needed to get the village of Evart incorporated. He was then elected president of Evart's city government, a position he held for four successive terms.
William A. Lewis died on May 7, 1917 in Evart, Michigan.
The William Augustus Lewis papers include biographical material, correspondence, Civil War files, and diaries relating to local and wartime activities, family matters, and professional activities. the papers are organized into the following series. Biographical, Correspondence, Civil War, Miscellaneous, and Diaries.
Subjects:
Evart (Mich.); Saginaw County (Mich.); Michigan--Social life and customs--1851-1860.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1861-1870.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1871-1880.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1881-1890.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1891-1900.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1901-1910.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1911-1920.; Michigan--Social life and customs--19th century.; Michigan--Social life and customs--20th century.; United States. Army. Michigan Infantry Regiment, 23rd (1862-1865). Company B.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.
- Biographical
  The Biographical series consists of biographical data, newspaper clippings, and printed materials about Lewis and his family. Also included here are articles Lewis wrote. These writings are interesting for several reasons: Lewis wrote them at the time of his experiences, thus affording us a contemporaneous account of events. Furthermore, Lewis's command of language and interesting writing style make for a vivid presentation of those events. Lastly, his writings discuss a variety of topics including the weather, geography, food, illnesses, exhaustion, money, traveling, Civil War letters and maneuvers, people, and events.
  - Handwritten articles by/about William A. Lewis (Box 1)
  - Newspaper articles by/about William A. Lewis (Box 1)
  - Newspaper articles by/about family members (Box 1)
  - "Accounts of 1) his Civil War experiences, 2) his trips to California in 1854, 1871 3) the settlement of Evart, Michigan as published in local newspapers" (Box 1)
  - Last Will and Testament 1914 (Box 1)
  - Speech circa 1885, original and copy (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  Correspondence, the second series, consists of letters of family, friends, and some federal government officials. The series spans the years 1840-1916 with large gaps missing for every year, either partially or totally. During the Civil War the letters are more regular and longer. They are mainly between Fred or William's future wife Sarah and William. These letters discuss geography, camp life, battles, traveling, illness, homesickness, loneliness, theft, assault, and depression. From the end of the War to Fred's death in 1890, the bulk of the correspondence is between Fred and William discussing business and family. With Fred's death the bulk of the letters are between William and his son Fred. Fred's letters discuss his college years in East Lansing and his hospitalization in Reed City, while William wrote of tours and family affairs. When not writing to Fred, William wrote the federal government to try to get larger pensions for Civil War veterans. Regardless of the gaps, this series offers several interesting perspectives on life in Michigan from 1840 to 1916, although it is not as complete a run of documentation as the Diaries series.
  - 1840, 1845, 1850, 1853, 1863 (Box 1)
  - 1864-1868 (Box 1)
  - 1872-1875, 1878-1879 (Box 1)
  - 1882-1883, 1885-1886, 1890-1894, 1898 (Box 1)
  - 1903-1904, 1907, 1909-1910, 1912, 1914-1916, undated (Box 1)
- Civil War
  Civil War is the third series. This series includes official correspondence, rosters, ordnance stores and receipts, as well as reminiscences and reunion miscellanea. The official correspondence spans 1863-65 and is composed of orders and letters between Lewis and General Headquarters or other officers concerning misconduct, theft and loss of supplies, and assault of officers (namely Lewis). The correspondence also documents the strict and interesting procedure of collecting evidence for arrests and trials during the Civil War.
  Both of the Civil War reminiscences are in Lewis's handwriting and were written after the Civil War at an unspecified date, probably 1870, with references to his diaries that survived the war. These writings are unfinished and record, chronologically, the maneuvers and battles through most of 1862-63. Besides the correspondence and the lists there is not much of great interest in this series.
  - Official correspondence 1863-1864 (Box 1)
  - Official correspondence 1865 (Box 1)
  - Rosters 1863-1865 (Box 1)
  - Ordnance stores, and receipts 1862-1863 (Box 1)
  - Ordnance stores, and receipts 1864 (Box 1)
  - Ordnance stores, and receipts 1865, undated (Box 1)
  - Reminiscences (2) undated (Box 1)
  - Reunion miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous
  Miscellaneous consists of assorted certificates of membership, account books, and scrapbooks. The scrapbooks are of the most importance as they consist of clippings, some of which were written by Lewis during and after the Civil War when he was a correspondent for Fred's newspaper. In these articles Lewis wrote of skirmishes, battles, illness, and great despair. His articles on early Evart mention its settlement and early development. His writings are second in importance only to his diaries.
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Account books 1846, 2 volumes (Box 1)
  - Account book 1899-1917 (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook circa 1869 (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook circa 1879-1885 (Box 1)
- Diaries, 1854-1917, 46 volumes (in 5 expanding files)
  The last series consists of Lewis's Diaries which span 1854 to 1917 with a few years missing. With far fewer gaps and more regularity than most of the Correspondence, this series is the most important one in this collection. It offers an informative view of a long and active life. In the earlier diaries, William wrote mostly of daily life. Diaries that cover the Civil War usually contain the briefest entries, but are still almost always on a daily basis. The entries usually discuss maneuvers, battles, and skirmishes. From 1865 until 1890, the diaries again record daily events. After Fred's death in 1890, the entries slant heavily towards William's son, Fred. Special court cases he was involved in, and family gatherings or visits receive more detail, especially after 1900.
  - 1854-1855 (Box 2)
    (typescript copy available)
  - 1856 (Box 2)
  - 1857 (Box 2)
  - 1857 (Box 2)
    (in 1 volume)
  - 1858 (Box 2)
  - 1859 (Box 2)
  - 1860 (Box 2)
  - 1862-1864 (Box 2)
  - 1862-1863 1900-1902 (Box 2)
  - 1866 (Box 2)
  - 1867 (Box 2)
  - 1869 (Box 2)
  - 1872 (Box 2)
  - 1873 (Box 2)
  - 1875 (Box 2)
  - 1891 (Box 2)
  - 1892 (Box 2)
  - 1894 (Box 2)
  - 1897-1900 (Box 2)
  - 1902-1903 (Box 2)
  - 1903-1904 (Box 2)
  - 1905 (Box 2)
  - 1906 (Box 2)
  - 1907 (Box 2)
  - 1908 (Box 2)
  - 1909, 2 volumes (Box 2)
  - 1910 (Box 2)
  - 1911 (Box 2)
  - 1912 (Box 2)
  - 1913 (Box 2)
  - 1914-1915 (Box 2)
  - 1916-1917 (Box 2)
  - 1917 (Box 2)